Right now the ninth פרק perek and this is the last פרק
perek and similarly to the previous one where all the משניות mishnayot
were put up front, here too the first משנה mishnah is really
all of the משניות mishnayot of the פרק. perek. And this one
focuses on ברכת השבח. Birchas HaShevach. We finally move away from meals
and get to ברכת השבח. Birchas HaShevach. Let's take a look. הרואה
מקום שנעשו בו נסים לישראל, Ha-ro'eh makom shena'asu bo nissim l'Yisrael, somebody
saw a place that miracles were done to the Jewish people, אומר
ברוך שעשה נסים לאבותינו במקום הזה. omer baruch she'asa nissim la-avoteinu bamkom
hazeh. Blessed is God who did miracles to our forefathers in this
place. מקום שנעקר ממנו עכום, Makom shena'akar mimenu akum, a place that
idolatry has been completely eradicated, אומר omer and it's presumably in Israel,
ברוך שעקר עכום מארצנו. baruch she'akar akum me'artzeinu. Now this does not
mean the people, it means idolatry, blessed is God who uprooted, right,
the whole Torah went in דברים Devarim is all about going into
the land and removing all the idolatry. So if there was a
place that actually that succeeded, and of course this is being written
in the time of pagan Rome where everywhere they turned they see
icons and images everywhere. So if you actually have a place that's
free of that, you make the ברכה bracha that you have uprooted
idolatry from our land.
Is he saying the people or the actual idol?
No, the idols, idolatry.
Even they're calling it עכום, Akum, which is like just often taking,
you're saying like the
צלם, tzelem, like the אשרה. ashera. The משנה Mishnah actually says עבודה
זרה.
avodah zarah.
Yes, עבודה זרה avodah zarah is original text, correct.
So the actual image, right?
Yes. Idolatry, I think I said it multiple times. Yes, idolatry. Okay.
על הזיקים ועל הזועות ועל הרעמים. Al hizzikim ve'al ha-zeva'ot ve'al ha-re'amim.
On זיקים hizzikim and זועות, zeva'ot, which are certain types of like
frightening or whatever, you know, aspects, whatever, not
no, not demons. Whatever. It's like lightning and so on. We'll talk
about what they are in the גמרא. Gemara. Lightning, thunder, not thunder,
that's coming up. Anyway, different types of weather events or something. ועל
הרעמים ve'al ha-re'amim and on thunder, ועל הרוחות ve'al ha-ruchot or winds,
probably means like tornadoes, ועל הברקים ve'al ha-berakim and lightning, אומר ברוך
שכחו וגבורתו מלא עולם. omer baruch she-kocho u-gevurato malei olam. Blessed is
God whose power and might fills the world. And we actually distinguish
a ברכה bracha between lightning and thunder. This משנה Mishnah has the
same. Now I should use this opportunity to take a pause and
say this is first of all a משנה Mishnah that actually has
the text. I don't think that we've had any before the texts
in the משניות mishnayot prior to this. But and interestingly the what's
missing from the text is ברוך אתה ה׳ אלקינו מלך העולם, Baruch
Atah Hashem Elokeinu Melech HaOlam, just the beginning and the end. That
might just be because he doesn't want to write God's name, it's
inferred. But look at תוספות, Tosafos, first תוספות Tosafos he says פירוש
מן השמיא, perush min ha-shamaya, that all of these ברכות brachos need
הזכרת שם ומלכות, hazkarat shem u-malchut, ברוך אתה ה׳ אלקינו מלך העולם.
Baruch Atah Hashem Elokeinu Melech HaOlam. And we know we do that
for lightning and thunder and so on, that's how we פוסק, pasken,
but there are a number of ראשונים Rishonim that say not, that
say that all of these ברכות brachos are without שם ומלכות, shem
u-malchut, that they never got the full weight of a classic ברכה
bracha and they were ways in which you say a שבח, shevach,
but they were more like תפילות tefillot than ברכות brachos and they
never got a שם ומלכות. shem u-malchut. But we assume and we
פוסק pasken that it is with שם ומלכות. shem u-malchut.
He says אבל aval they're not סמוך לחברתה, samuch l'chaverta, right?
Well right, but what if, but if they were a real ברכה
bracha they would require it. But the problem is that this משנה
Mishnah never mentions שם ומלכות. shem u-malchut.
So are we supposed to believe even though they're not סמוך לחברתה
samuch l'chaverta that they we'd say it?
Some people say you don't say it because they're not a real
ברכה. bracha. Essentially they're like a תפילה tefillah more than a ברכה.
bracha. So that's the question. So because the text isn't in and
we פוסק pasken they're a real ברכה bracha and we say it
with שם ומלכות. shem u-malchut. Now goes on, על הימים ועל הנהרות,
al ha-yammim ve'al ha-neharot, on oceans and rivers, presumably it means like
a very unusual river, powerful rivers or something, ועל המדברות ve'al ha-midbarot
or on, you know, wildernesses, deserts, אומר ברוך עושה מעשה בראשית. omer
baruch oseh ma'aseh bereishit. Okay.
Also a question, what if you're these you frequently see these, you
know, we generally פוסק pasken if you haven't within 30 days. רבי
יהודה אומר הרואה את הים הגדול, Rabbi Yehuda omer ha-ro'eh et ha-yam
ha-gadol, if you see the Mediterranean, אומר ברוך שעשה את הים הגדול,
omer baruch she'asa et ha-yam ha-gadol, the Great Sea. Of course it's
a little funny you see the Atlantic or Pacific, you don't say
ים הגדול Yam HaGadol but you see the Mediterranean, you do.
What do you mean ים הגדול Yam HaGadol mean like a big
ocean?
No, הים הגדול ha-Yam ha-Gadol is the Mediterranean. Okay. בזמן שרואהו לפרקים
bizman she-ro'eihu l'prakim
and here you get the idea if you see it only occasionally.
If you're seeing it all the time then it's nothing special or
you don't, you lose the, you become desensitized to it. על הגשמים
ועל הבשורות טובות Al ha-geshamim ve'al ha-besorot tovot when it rains or
on good reports, presumably rain and and from the agricultural perspective you
need those rains, and then otherwise good report, אומר ברוך הטוב והמטיב.
omer baruch hatov vehamativ. Blessed is the one God who is good
and does good. על בשורות רעות Al besorot ra'ot or some say
שמועות רעות shemu'ot ra'ot on bad reports, something bad happened and you
heard about it, ואומר ברוך דיין האמת. ve-omer baruch dayan ha-emet. Okay,
now how bad does it have to be to say דיין האמת?
dayan ha-emet? Again, all this to be discussed. בנה בית חדש וקנה
כלים חדשים. Bana bayit chadash ve-kana kelim chadashim. You built a new
house, you purchased new
objects, אומר ברוך שהחיינו וקימנו והגיענו לזמן הזה. omer baruch shehecheyanu vekiyemanu
vehigianu lazman hazeh. You say שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu. Again, the question for us
becomes בית חדש bayit chadash certainly, but how much about buying a
new suit? I mean how fancy is a suit? How expensive is
a suit? How frequently do you do it? For us it's not
as big of a deal a lot of the time than it
was in the גמרא Gemara or in the time of the משנה,
Mishnah, but. When it is a significant thing, then you do make
the ברכה beracha, *Beracha*. They tell an interesting story that רב הרצוג
*Rav Herzog* when they announced
the when the Israel declared independence, I forget whether it was the
UN vote or Israel declared independence. Anyway, he got up and he
said: ברוך אתה ה' אלוהינו מלך העולם שהחיינו וקימנו והגיענו לזמן הזה
*Baruch Atah Hashem Elokeinu Melech Haolam Shehecheyanu V'kiyemanu V'higiyanu Lazman Hazeh*. And
somebody standing next to him said, Isaac Herzog, how do you think
you make the ברכה beracha *Beracha*? Where do you know that Halachically
you're able to make a ברכה Bracha *Beracha* for something like this?
He said, you don't understand. He said, I'm wearing a new tie.
So, oh, okay.
So,
it's cheap for a tie you make a ברכה Bracha *Beracha*, for
מדינה *Medinah* you don't make a ברכה Bracha, *Beracha*? So anyway, it
is a little bit funny that we focus שהחיינו *Shehecheyanu* on, oh,
a fruit, a suit, but we don't make שהחיינו *Shehecheyanu* on certain
types of things that aren't mentioned that are things that for us
are, you know, much more acquisitions of שמחה *Simcha*. כלים *Kelim* means
like clothes? Clothes, presumably.
But let's say you bought like something, you know, really nice?
Could be, could be. People that have been waiting for months for
their new iPhone 5 that just came out. So, okay, if it's
a big שמחה *Simcha*, the answer is yes. All right, הרע *Ha-ra*
now. מברך על הרע מעין על הטובה ועל הטובה מעין על הרע
*Mevarech al Ha-ra me-ein al Ha-tova v'al Ha-tova me-ein al Ha-ra*. You
make a ברכה Bracha *Beracha* for bad even if it is, you
know, literally means if it's of the similar or analogous to or
the essence of the good and from the good if it's sort
of in a similar way on the bad, which is very cryptic
and the גמרא gemara *Gemara* will discuss what that means. צועק לשעבר
הרי זו תפילת שוא *Tzo'ek l'shavar harei zo tefilat shav*. If you
cry out to God for something that's already happened, then it is
a, right, then it is a mindless prayer, a worthless prayer. היתה
אשתו מעוברת *Hayeta ishto u'uberet*, if your wife was pregnant, assuming we're
talking to a man, ואומר v'omer, יהי רצון שתלד אשתי זכר *v'omer
yehi ratzon she-teled ishti zachar*, I hope that it's a boy, הרי
זו תפילת שוא *harei zo tefilat shav*. It's a little late to
be praying for that, so that is a תפילת שוא *tefilat shav*.
היה בא בדרך ושמע קול צוחה בעיר *Haya ba-derech v'shama kol tzevacha
ba-ir*. You're going on the way and you heard that there's something
happening, there's a whole, you know, you see the ambulances, commotion racing
to a place. ואומר v'omer, יהי רצון שלא תהא זו בתוך ביתי
*v'omer yehi ratzon shelo tehei zo b'toch beiti*, oh my God, I
hope it's not in my house. הרי זו תפילת שוא *harei zo
tefilat shav*. That is a worthless prayer. Whatever happened, happened. Now, you
could hope that that wasn't what had happened, but to pray for
that would be, God is not going to change the past. Okay,
so it's no point about praying for that. All right, הנכנס לכרך
*ha-nichnas l'krach*, if you're going into a city, מתפלל שתים *mitpallel shtayim*.
You make two prayers. אחת בכניסתו ואחת ביציאתו *achat b'nichisato v'achat b'yitziato*,
one when you're entering, one when you're leaving. Which is interesting, although
we have תפילת הדרך *Tefilat Ha-derech*, that traveling is dangerous, but also
going into another city is dangerous. You know, there are all these
conmen and other types of people, things that you don't know about
the city, you have to be concerned about. So you make a
ברכה Bracha, *Beracha* both when you enter and when you leave.
This is an unfamiliar city to you?
Yeah, unfamiliar. בן עזאי אומר ארבע *Ben Azai omer arba*, four. שתים
בכניסתו ושתים ביציאתו *shtayim b'nichisato u'shtayim b'yitziato*, two in each direction. נותן
הודאה על שעבר *noten hoda'ah al she-avar*, each time you either enter
or leave, here's what you do according to him, you do two
ברכות berachos *Berachos*. נותן הודאה על שעבר *noten hoda'ah al she-avar*, you
thank God for saving you until now, protecting you until now. וצועק
על העתיד *v'tzo'ek al he-atid*, and you call out to God for
to help you for the future. I should also mention that it's
very interesting in this משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* that it uses the word
צועק *tzo'ek*, right, which is much more than like מתפלל *mitpallel*. You
know, you understand צועק *tzo'ek* when it sort of speaks about oh
my God, there's like a commotion, I hope that the fire engines
aren't running to my house. But it also gave the example about
I hope I have a son, you know. So it's interesting the
use of צועק *tzo'ek* for things that we would certainly be less,
you know, somehow tragic.
But so by the city again maybe it underscores the amount of
fear and anxiety in terms of going in the city, but it
is interesting that it's now using that verb as somewhat of a
generic verb. חייב אדם לברך על הרע כשם שמברך על הטובה *chayav
adam l'varech al ha-ra k'shem she-mevarech al ha-tova*. We sort of said
this before. You have to, but maybe it's reiterating it, you have
to bless God for even the bad thing the same way you
bless God for the good thing. שנאמר shenemar, *she-ne'emar*, meaning believing that
everything is from God and it all ultimately serves a positive purpose.
שנאמר ואהבת את ה' אלהיך בכל לבבך *she-ne'emar v'ahavta et Hashem Elokecha
b'chol levavecha*. Now what do you get from that idea? So here's
the דרשה *drasha*. בכל לבבך *b'chol levavecha* בשני יצריך *b'shnei yetzarecha*, your
two urges. יצר טוב ויצר הרע *yetzer tov v'yetzer ra*. Even your,
you know, evil urge, your, you know, more of your sort of,
you know, lusts and desires and so on, you have to find
a way to channel that and to use that to serve God.
Like the famous מדרש *Midrash* on the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* והנה טוב
מאד me'od, *v'hinei tov me'od* הרי זה יצר הרע *harei zeh yetzer
ha-ra*, so is a famous מדרש *Midrash* and the מדרש *Midrash* says
why? It says אלמלא יצר הרע לא בנה אדם בית ולא נשא
אשה *imlo yetzer ha-ra lo bana adam bayit, v'lo nasa isha*, right,
if it weren't for those urges, you would not ever try to
achieve things in the world, you wouldn't have a family and procreate,
so you find a way to use those types of urges in
constructive ways. ובכל נפשך *u'v'chol nafshecha*, with all of your soul, אפילו
הוא נוטל את נפשך *afilu hu notel et nafshecha*, prepared to give
up your life to serve God for the obligation of martyrdom. ובכל
מאדך *u'v'chol me'odecha*, all of your מאוד *me'od*, all of your wealth
or all of your ability. בכל ממונך *b'chol mamonecha*, all of your
wealth. דבר אחר *davar acher*, now we get to the דרשה *drasha*
why we're quoting it here. Every measure and measure בכל מידה middah,
ומידה, from מאד, me'od not much muchness, but
מידה, every measure and measure שהוא מודד לך, shehu moded lecha, that
God lays out for you, הרי מודה לו, harei modeh lo, so
reading מאד and also to thank him because normally we
read מידה כנגד מידה, middah k'neged middah, the same way you treat
other people, you will be given measure for measure by God. Okay,
that's not the point here. God does something bad for you, point
is don't do something bad towards God. Right, so it switches from
מודד moded to מודה. modeh. Whatever God hands out to you, you
should thank God for that regardless, like
קבל את כל מה שבא אליך בתמימות. kabel et kol mah sheba
elecha bitmimut. Exactly.
Everything is somehow serving a purpose and or like they say,
this is a to bless it,
not just to thank God, to believe that somehow it's serving some
good purpose. Right, so you get what you get and you don't
get upset. Okay, לא יקל אדם את ראשו lo yakel adam et
rosho כנגד שער המזרח. k'neged shaar hamizrach. Now there is a radical
sort of shift here after all this stuff about תפילות tefillot and
ברכות berachos and ברכת השבח, birkas hashevach, we have a little discussion
about what happens if you're going up to the בית המקדש. beis
hamikdash. Try to figure out what this is doing in this מסכת.
masechet. So you should not treat lightly כנגד שער המזרח k'neged shaar
hamizrach when you're standing opposite the eastern gate of הר הבית, har
habayis, שהוא מכוון כנגד בית קדשי הקדשים, shehu mechuvan k'neged beis kadshei
hakodashim, because it is in a direct line, you know, because the
entrances were all the east, they were lined up to get you
straight into the Holy of Holies. ולא יכנס להר הבית, v'lo yikanes
l'har habayis, don't go up on the Temple
Mount במקלו, bemaklo, במנעלו, bemin'alo, with your staff and with your shoes,
בפונדתו, befundato, your money belt, ובאבק שעל רגליו, uva'avak she'al raglav, dust
on your feet. You have to go in a very sort of
prepared and holy way. ולא יעשנו קפנדריא, v'lo ya'asenu kapandarya, you certainly
should not make it a shortcut cutting through הר הבית, har habayis,
ורקיקה, v'rakika, and don't spit in it, קל וחומר, kal vachomer, you
can as a from these other things. Now and then back to
כל חותמי ברכות שבמקדש, kol chotmei berachos shebamikdash, the way they would
seal ברכות Brachos? in the מקדש, mikdash, מן העולם ועד העולם. min
ha'olam ve'ad ha'olam. So it's the way they would end a ברכה,
Bracha, right, is ברוך אתה ה' אלקי ישראל מן העולם ועד העולם,
baruch atah Hashem Elokei Yisrael min ha'olam ve'ad ha'olam, and then they
would say ברוך חונן הדעת, baruch chonen hadaat, so the end of
a ברכה Bracha, in the מקדש, mikdash, it would end with עד
העולם. ad ha'olam. God is blessed forever and ever.
משקלקלו הצדוקים mishekilelu hatzedokim or המינים, haminim, once there was a it
was sort of you know the מינים minim or the heretics or
the or the sectarians or the צדוקים tzedokim started to make trouble.
What was the trouble? So the גמרא gemara, says that they basically
said that God only there's only one world, there's not a world
to come. Which is why
now according to Josephus, right, I'm trying to remember, did the צדוקים
tzedokim not believe in the world to come? He basically makes and
I don't remember. Anyway, the גמרא, gemara you know the גמרא Gemara
in I don't think the צדוקים tzedokim I think they did believe
in the world to come, I don't remember.
There's in the Christian scriptures, there's actually a specific statement that they
did not.
They did not believe in the world to come. So צדוקים tzedokim
here actually might be right. Sometimes צדוקים tzedokim is a sort of
censoring of מינים. minim. I didn't get a chance to check the
manuscripts, but that might
be right. It says in the manuscript מינים. minim. מינים? minim?
So that's interesting. I don't know, because anyway, normally מינים minim means
means Jewish Christians and Christians certainly believed in the world to come.
So I don't know. Anyway, it definitely was some sect that did
not believe in the world to come. We know that that was
an issue for חז"ל chazal because in סנהדרין sanhedrin they said anybody
who says אין תחיית המתים מן התורה ein techiyat hameitim min hatorah
doesn't have a חלק לעולם הבא, chelek l'olam haba, so that was
definitely an issue. There were definitely those who were saying that. So
it was not enough to say God is blessed עד העולם, ad
ha'olam, ואמרו, v'amru, so they and these what did these צדוקים tzedokim
say? אין עולם אלא אחד, ein olam ela echad, there's only one
world. התקינו שיהיו אומרים מן העולם ועד העולם, hitkinu sheyiyu omrim min
ha'olam ve'ad ha'olam,
from this world till the next, from one world to the next.
התקינו שיהא אדם שואל בשלום חברו בשם, hitkinu she'ei adam sho'el b'shalom
chaveiro b'shem, that's one תקנה takana they made. They also by the
way made a תקנה takana that a person should ask after the
welfare of his friend בשם, b'shem, with God's name, שנאמר, as it
says, והנה בעז בא מבית לחם ויאמר לקוצרים ה' עמכם ויאמרו לו
יברכך ה'. v'hinei Boaz ba mibeis lechem vayomer lakotzrim Hashem imachem vayomru
lo yevarechecha Hashem. Boaz greeted the
harvesters by saying may God be with you, ויאמרו לו יברכך ה',
vayomru lo yevarechecha Hashem, God should bless you. So you use God's
name in greeting people and it's not and it's not considered an
inappropriate use of God's name.
ואומר, v'omer, ה' עמך גבור החיל, Hashem imcha gibor hachayil, God is
with you oh you know mighty person, this is what the מלאך
malach said. So anyway you see it's proper to use God's name,
so they established this as a regular way of greeting people. ואומר,
אל תבוז כי זקנה אמך, al tivuz ki ziknah imecha, do not
show disrespect because your mother has grown old, which is we sort
of like the way it's read is you should follow the teachings
of the זקני עמך, ziknei amecha, of the elders of your people.
So follow the example set by Boaz and greet people with God's
name. ואומר, עת לעשות לה' הפרו תורתך. et la'asot la'Hashem heiferu toratecha.
What's the הפרו תורתך? heiferu toratecha? So רב נתן Rav Natan says
הפרו תורתך, heiferu toratecha, we're prepared to even
violate the Torah. משום עת לעשות לה' mishum eis la'asos l'Hashem to
serve God. Now of course that can be very dangerous. רש"י Rashi
reemphasizes multiple times, twice or three times in his commentary in the
משנה, Mishnah it can look like we're doing something wrong,
or how bad of the wrong thing. But the point, what's so
wrong about what you're doing? So the point here seems רש"י Rashi
says is the concern of, you know, using שם השם, Shem Hashem,
maybe it's not respectful to use God in a normal daily greeting.
Now it's a very interesting way to end the מסכת Masechet with
this whole idea about using God's name in a greeting and all
this whole thing about the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. How's that relevant
to God's greeting maybe, but how's that relevant to all this stuff
about the ברכות? It might be similar to the way that the
מסכת Masechet began. Let us not forget that the מסכת Masechet began
with that you say קריאת שמע Krias Shema at the time when
the כהנים Kohanim go down to their טבילה. tvilah. And it's sort
of like framing, it's very interesting that the whole מסכת ברכות Masechet
Brachos is framed with a reference to the מקדש. Mikdash. And a
lot of this might be how do you bring that מקדש Mikdash
into your daily life in a post מקדש Mikdash world? So holding
on for instance to this image of going up to הר הבית
Har HaBayis and how do you act respectfully on הר הבית, Har
HaBayis, that was that קדושה, kedusha, and now what we're doing is,
you know what, even every single day you greet somebody, you can
sort of bring a certain קדושה kedusha into that, even though that
might not be sort of that, you know, the same as in
the מקדש Mikdash which was only in one place and here it's
somewhat in a sort of more mundane context. But it's very interesting
how the מסכת Masechet begins and opens with that mention of מקדש.
Mikdash. Let's just read one line in the גמרא Gemara to get
a little bit further. מנא הני מילי, Mina hani mili, where do
you know this idea that you're supposed to say a ברכה Bracha.
in a place where miracles were done? אמר רבי יוחנן דאמר קרא,
Amar Rabbi Yochanan d'amar Kra, the פסוק says, ויאמר ישראל ברוך ה'
אשר הציל, Vayomer Yisroel Baruch Hashem asher hitzil, look ישראל Yisroel did
it. It's good enough for ישראל, Yisroel, it's good enough for us.
So now the גמרא Gemara says אניסא דרבים מברכינן, Anissa d'rabim mevorchinan,
so the גמרא Gemara, says so you need to tell me you
make a ברכה Bracha, on a miracle that happens to the masses.
But אניסא דיחיד לא מברכינן, Anissa d'yachid lo mevorchinan, not to an
individual? Because it only said ניסין
לישראל. nisin l'Yisroel. דההוא גברא, d'ha hu gavra, there was a person,
דהוה קאזיל בעבר ימינא, d'hava ka'azil b'Avar Yemina, he was going in
this place עבר ימינא, Avar Yemina, נפל ליה אריה, nafleh lei aryeh,
a lion attacked him, איתעביד ליה ניסא, isaveid lei nisa, a miracle
happened, ואיציל מיניה, v'itzil minei, and he was saved. אתא לקמיה דרבא,
Ata l'kamei d'Rava, he came to רבא, Rava, ואמר ליה, v'amar lei,
and רבא Rava said to him, כל אימת דמטית להתם, kol eimas
d'matyas l'hasam, anytime you pass that place, בריך, barich, you make a
ברכה, Bracha, ברוך שעשה לי נס במקום הזה. Baruch she'asah li nes
b'makom hazeh. That's the ברכה Bracha. that God you did a miracle.
ומר בריה דרבינא, U'Mar brei d'Ravina, and another story, מר Mar the
son of רבינא, Ravina, הוה קאזיל בפיסקא דערבות, hava ka'azil b'Piska d'Aravot,
was going in the valley of ערבות, Aravot, צחא למיא, tzacha l'maya,
he was thirsty for water, maybe he was thirsting to death, ואיתעביד
ליה ניסא, v'isaveid lei nisa, a miracle occurred, ואיעי עיינא דמיא, v'yevei
einah d'maya, and a wellspring of water popped up out of nowhere,
ואישתי, v'ishtei, and he drank. ותו, V'tu, another time, זימנא חדא הוה
קאזיל
בריסתקא דמחוזא, zimna chada hava ka'azil b'ristka d'Mechuza, one time he was
going in the
marketplace of מחוזא. Mechuza.
Where were we? ונפל ליה גמלא פריצא, v'nafleh lei gamla pritza, and
a wild camel started like
attacking and it could have really killed him or hurt him.
איספלקא ליה אשישתא, ispalga lei ashisa, and what happened was that a
wall fell down, על גבי, al gabei, and he went into the
building
that
the fallen wall had opened for him, and he got saved. כי
מטא לערבות, Ki mitya l'Aravot, when he came to the place of
ערבות, Aravot, בריך, barich, made a ברכה, ברוך שעשה לי נס בערבות
ובגמלא. Baruch she'asah li nes b'Aravot u'v'gamla. He didn't just say in
this place, he actually referred to the two miracles that occurred to
him, but he started with the ערבות, Aravot, that was the place
of the water. וכי מטא לריסתקא דמחוזא, V'ki mitya l'ristka d'Mechuza, when
he went again into the marketplace of מחוזא, Mechuza, בריך ברוך שעשה
לי נס בגמלא ובערבות, barich Baruch she'asah li nes b'gamla u'v'Aravot, blessed
is God that did the miracle and
now he reversed the order with the camel and with the ערבות.
Aravot. Interesting, he felt that he had the liberty to personalize it,
not just נס במקום הזה. nes b'makom hazeh. Anyway, he personalized it.
Anyway, so you see and he put both. You see, says the
גמרא, even an individual makes a ברכה, not just for נס לישראל.
nes l'Yisroel. אמרי אניסא דרבים כולי עלמא מיחייבי לברוכי. Amri anissa d'rabim
kuli alma mechayvei l'vruchei. If it was a miracle for כלל ישראל,
Klal Yisroel, everybody makes the ברכה, even if it was like way
back when in history and it wasn't you personally. אניסא דיחיד, Anissa
d'yachid, if it was a personal miracle, איהו חייב לברוכי, ihu chayav
l'vruchei, then you, the one who experienced it, makes the ברכה. Other
people do not make a ברכה, and that's the difference. So the
משנה says a miracle for כלל ישראל, Klal Yisroel, even what was
way back when in history, everybody makes the ברכה, but if it's
for you personally, then yes, you personally would make that ברכה.